Guide to the Rosetta Reitz Papers, 1929-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Rosetta Reitz papers 1929-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Reitz, Rosetta, 1924-2008.
41 linear feet Extent: 30,750 Items
Rosetta Reitz (1924-2008) was a business owner, stock broker, university lecturer, and writer on issues including food, feminism, women's health, and female jazz and blues musicians. She was also the founder and owner of Rosetta Records, a company most prominent in the 1980s that was dedicated to re-releasing historic recordings by female jazz and blues musicians. The Rosetta Reitz Papers address aspects of the entirety of Reitz's career, with the majority related to Rosetta Records and to Reitz's associated music research since the 1970s. The collection contains company documents, research notes, manuscripts, correspondence, newspaper clippings, photocopies, photographs, a variety of audio and moving image formats, as well as magazines and books.
RL.01079
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In addition, all original audio and moving image materials are CLOSED to patron listening and/or viewing. However, researchers can access the original artifacts for the purpose of reading liner notes and carrying out other text-based studies. Scanned images of all LP covers and liner notes are available in JPEG format on DVD 1 in Box 58. CD or DVD use copies, which are OPEN to patron use, are available for some items and are noted below. Unless otherwise noted, use copies must be made for access to audio and moving image content.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Rosetta Reitz Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in May 2009 and June 2010.
Biographical Note
Rosetta Reitz (née Goldman) was born in Utica, New York on September 28, 1924, the youngest of six children. After graduating from the Utica Free Academy at the age of 16, Reitz studied at the University of Buffalo, Syracuse University, and the University of Wisconsin. In 1945, she moved to New York City, where, aside from a brief time living in New Jersey in the 1950s, she would spend the remainder of her life. Reitz married Robert Reitz in the mid-1940s, with whom she had three daughters prior to their divorce in 1963.
During the course of her career, Reitz was involved in a variety of entrepreneurial ventures. She owned several businesses, including the Four Seasons Book Shop (1946-1954), the Four Seasons Greeting Card Company (1954-1961), and Rosetta Records (1979-2008). She worked as a representative and a stock broker for several financial institutions (1967-1970), and she was a newspaper columnist at the Village Voice on issues of food (1958-1963), feminism (1971), and jazz (1973). Reitz lectured at numerous universities on topics including food history (1960-1961), menopause and women's health (1973-1977), and the history of female blues and jazz musicians (1977-2000s). Reitz was also the author of several published books and articles on mushrooms (and food more broadly), menopause (and women's health and feminism more broadly), the blues, and jazz. Among her many honors and awards are: a Wonder Woman Award (1982), a Grandmother Winifred Grant (1994), the International Association of Jazz Educators Outstanding Service Award (1998), and the Veteran Feminists of America Honor Roll (2002). Reitz passed away on November 1, 2008 from issues related to cardiopulmonary disease.
Collection Overview
The Rosetta Reitz Papers span the dates 1929-2008, with the bulk of the material covering the period of the late 1970s through the 2000s. While the collection addresses aspects of the entirety of her career, the vast majority is related to Rosetta Records and Reitz's related music research. The collection is divided into eight series: Biographical Information, Rosetta Records Business Files, Presentations, Writings, Photographs, Posters, Audio and Moving Images, and Reference Materials.
The Biographical Information Series contains published and unpublished writings, correspondence, resume materials, and scrapbooks by and about Rosetta Reitz.
The Rosetta Records Business Files Series contains materials related to the founding of Rosetta Records in 1979 and its daily operations in the decades that followed, which primarily focus on the design and production of the company's catalog releases. Also of note are the files related to Reitz's involvement with Greta Schiller and Andrea Weiss in creating a documentary film on the International Sweethearts of Rhythm.
Print materials related to the many concerts, lectures, presentations, and courses that Reitz produced and/or taught on jazz, the blues, and other topics are found in the Presentations Series. Of note are the files related to Reitz's numerous presentations of Shouters and Wailers, which was an evolving film-based lecture that Reitz delivered throughout the U.S. as well as overseas, that focused on female jazz and blues musicians.
The Writings Series contains manuscript drafts, research notes, and other materials related to Reitz's written works on food, feminism and women's health, and female jazz and blues musicians, including writing related to her grassroots advocacy for the creation of a US postage stamp honoring Bessie Smith.
The Photographs Series primarily contains 8x10 publicity photographs of various jazz and blues musicians, along with other candid photographs from Reitz's life and career.
Oversize promotional materials, primarily related to Reitz's film-based Shouters and Wailers presentations, but also related to individual female jazz and blues musicians, are located in the Posters Series.
The Audio and Moving Image Series contains all of the commercial releases by Rosetta Records in cassette, LP, and/or CD formats, including recordings featuring Ida Cox, Dorothy Donegan, Lil Green, the International Sweethearts of Rhythm, Valaida Snow, Rosetta Tharpe, Dinah Washington, Ethel Waters, Mae West, Georgia White, and others. It also contains audio recordings of the Blues is a Woman concerts, hosted by Carmen McRae, that Reitz produced for the Kool Jazz Festival and the Newport Jazz Festival in the early 1980s. Also a part of the series are VHS and 16mm film of musical performances by female jazz and blues musicians that originally aired on television and that Reitz compiled as a part of her ongoing research. Original audio and moving image materials are closed to listening and viewing. However, researchers can access the original artifacts for the purpose of reading liner notes and carrying out other text-based studies. Scanned images of all LP covers and liner notes are available in JPEG format on DVD 1 in Box 58. CD or DVD use copies, which are open to patron use, are available for some items and are noted below. Unless otherwise noted, use copies must be made for access to audio and moving image content.
The Reference Materials Series contains newspaper clippings, magazines, and books, primarily related to jazz and the blues, that Reitz drew upon in the course of her ongoing research and writing.
Subject Headings
16mm; Audiocassettes; Blues musicians; Clippings; CD-ROMs; Cox, Ida, 1889-1967; Donegan, Dorothy; Feminism; Food writing; Green, Lil, 1919-1954; International Sweethearts of Rhythm; Jazz; Jazz musicians; Kool Jazz Festival; Long-playing records; McRae, Carmen; Menopause; Mushrooms; Newport Jazz Festival; Photographs; Record labels; Reitz, Rosetta; Rosetta Records (Firm); Schiller, Greta; Scrapbooks; Smith, Bessie, 1894-1937; Snow, Valaida; Tharpe, Rosetta, d. 1973; Videocassettes; Washington, Dinah, 1924-1963; Waters, Ethel, 1896-1977; Weiss, Andrea; West, Mae; White, Georgia, 1903-1980; Women -- Health and hygiene; Women blues musicians; Women jazz musicians; Women jazz musicians -- United States
Contents of Collection
- Biographical Information Series, 1958-2008, (3 boxes)
  Contains biographical and autobiographical information by and about Rosetta Reitz, including her work both inside and outside the music business. Comprises published and unpublished writings, correspondence, resume materials, and scrapbooks.
  - Autobiographical Writings and Biographical Files, 1967-2008, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    Autobiographical sketches by Reitz as well as published articles and obituaries on Reitz. There are also files documenting some of Reitz's numerous music-related concerts, lectures, and presentations.
  - Personal Correspondence, 1958-2004, (13 folders) (Box 1)
    Correspondence with various family members, as well as Sippie Wallace, Dick Weissman, Caroline Robinson, Duncan Scheidt, Connie Berry, Francis Smith, Maurica King, Dick Newmark, Ron Lofman, and others.
  - Awards, 1981-2004, (4 folders) (Box 1)
    Correspondence, certificates, press releases, newspaper clippings, and other material related to various grants and awards Reitz received, including the Wonder Woman Award (1982), a Grandmother Winifred Grant (1994), the International Association of Jazz Educators Outstanding Service Award (1998), and the Veteran Feminists of America Honor Roll (2002).
  - Job Application Materials, 1963-1993, (6 folders) (Box 1)
    Correspondence, clippings, articles, resumes, job applications, and other material related to Reitz's work as a stockbroker, bookstore owner, magazine columnist, and university professor, as well as her consulting work on issues of music, food, and women's health.
  - Scrapbooks (Box 2-3)
    Two scrapbooks compiled by Reitz that contain a variety of newspaper clippings relating to Reitz, Rosetta Records, and various female jazz and blues musicians.
- Rosetta Records Business Files Series, 1978-2002, (4 boxes)
  Rosetta Records was founded by Reitz in 1979, and the company released a total of eighteen recordings and one film, all related to female jazz and blues musicians. While the company was most active in the 1980s, Rosetta Records continued to release recordings into the 1990s. The majority of this series contains materials related to the founding of the company and the design and manufacturing of its catalog releases. An additional eight folders document Reitz's involvement in a documentary film project about the International Sweethearts of Rhythm.
  - Catalog Releases
    Contains liner note text, artist research, elements of cover design, and related correspondence. Arranged by official Rosetta Records catalog numbers.
    - 1300: Mean Mothers (Box 4)
    - 1301: Women's Railroad Blues, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1302: Red, White, and Blues (Box 4)
    - 1303: Piano Singers' Blues (Box 4)
    - 1304: Ida Cox - Wild Women Don't Have The Blues (Box 4)
    - 1305: Valaida Snow - Hot Snow (Box 4)
    - 1306: Big Mamas (Box 4)
    - 1307: Georgia White - Sings and Plays (Box 4)
    - 1308: Super Sisters (Box 4)
    - 1309: Boogie Blues (Box 4)
    - 1310: Lil Green - Chicago 1940-1947 (Box 4)
    - 1311: Sweet Petunias (Box 4)
    - 1312: The International Sweethearts of Rhythm (Box 4)
    - 1313: Dinah Washington - Wise Woman's Blues (Box 4)
    - 1314: Ethel Waters - 1938-1939, The Complete Bluebird Sessions (Box 4)
    - 1315: Mae West - Sixteen Sultry Songs (Box 4)
    - 1316: Jailhouse Blues, (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1317: Sister Rosetta Tharpe - Sacred and Secular, Gospel-Blues-Jazz (Box 5)
    - 1318: Dorothy Donegan - Dorothy Romps, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1320: Jazz Women On Video - 1932-1952 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Project Ideas, (3 folders) (Box 5)
      Ideas for future catalog releases, including related correspondence, with plans for a release devoted to June Richmond and a compilation tentatively titled S+M Blues.
    - Manufacturing Files, (7 folders) (Box 5)
      Records related to the physical production of the catalog releases, including notes on barcode design, invoices from the Hauppauge Record Manufacturing company, and ideas for CD and LP label design. Two folders contain photocopies of photographic images related to possible releases.
  - International Sweethearts of Rhythm Documentary, 1981-1990
    These records pertain to Rosetta Reitz's involvement in a documenary film project about the International Sweethearts of Rhythm. Reitz met independent film producers Greta Schiller and Andrea Weiss in 1983, and the three, along with Reitz's daughter Rebecca, began to share creative responsibilities for the project. In 1986, with much of the work on the film completed, Reitz parted company with Schiller and Weiss over creative differences and disagreements over copyright license issues. Schiller and Weiss retained control of the project and began showing the finished film in late 1986. A large part of this series comprises legal correspondence and memoranda regarding the dispute between the parties, which lasted until 1990.
    - Grant Applications (Box 6)
    - Invoices (Box 6)
    - Film Showings (Box 6)
    - Legal Files, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Project Files (Box 6)
    - Permissions (Box 6)
    - Correspondence (Box 6)
  - Record Reviews, 1980-1992, (3 folders) (Box 6)
    Published reviews of various releases from the Rosetta Records catalog. Also contains homemade press clippings assembled by Reitz from published reviews.
  - Advertisements, 1985-1986 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    Contains print advertisements and press releases, along with related materials, for Rosetta Records. Also contains order forms for postcards of female jazz and blues musicians, created by Rosetta Records.
  - Company Correspondence, 1979-2002 (Box 6)
    Contains a variety of correspondence between Reitz and fans, critics, scholars, and others related to Rosetta Records. One folder is devoted to correspondence and other materials related to the Smithsonian Institution recording project The Story of the Blues.
  - Legal and Financial Files, 1978-1999
    Invoices, order forms, licensing agreements, and other documents related to Rosetta Records.
    - Detroit Public Library Invoices (Box 7)
    - Music Exchange Invoices (Box 7)
    - Paradox Invoices (Box 7)
    - Pollyjazz Invoices (Box 7)
    - Catalog Order Forms (Box 7)
    - Copyright Licensing Agreements (Box 7)
    - Financial Information (Box 7)
    - Chelsea Mini Storage (Box 7)
- Presentations Series, 1980-1996, (3 boxes)
  Includes print materials related to concerts Reitz produced, along with lectures, presentations, and courses Reitz designed. For related photographs and audio recordings, see Photographs Series and Audio and Video Recordings Series.
  - Blues Is a Woman, 1980-1990 (Box 8)
    A concert produced by Reitz emphasizing the history of female blues singers, hosted by Carmen McRae. Contains correspondence, programs, reviews, financial information, drafts of scripts, and related information for the performances at the Newport Jazz Festival at Avery Fisher Hall (1980), the Hollywood Bowl (1981), and Boston's Symphony Hall (1990).
  - Wild Women Don't Have the Blues, 1981, (8 folders) (Box 8)
    A concert produced by Reitz featuring live performances by Nell Carter, Linda Hopkins, and Sippie Wallace along with choreography, film clips, and photographic slides. Series contains correspondence, programs, reviews, financial information, drafts of scripts, and related information for the performance at the Kool Jazz Festival at Avery Fisher Hall (1981).
  - Women Blow Their Own Horns, 1981 (Box 9)
    A concert produced by Reitz and hosted by Melba Tolliver at the Kool Jazz Festival at Carnegie Hall (1981) featuring over twenty female jazz instrumentalists and ensembles. Folder contains correspondence, programs, reviews, drafts of scripts, and related information.
  - Shouters and Wailers, 1982-1996
    An evolving presentation by Reitz based on numerous film clips of early female jazz and blues musicians. Series contains correspondence, programs, and related materials and is arranged alphabetically by location of presentation.
    - Film Inquiries (Box 9)
    - Boston, 1983 (Box 9)
    - Brown University, 1982 (Box 9)
    - Collective for Living Cinema, 1983 (Box 9)
    - College of Wooster, 1984 (Box 9)
    - Cornell University, 1985 (Box 9)
    - Davis and Elkins College, 1995 (Box 9)
    - Detroit, 1982 (Box 9)
    - Germany - Festival der Frauen, 1988, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Harvard University (Box 9)
    - Indiana, 1984 (Box 9)
    - Jersey City College, 1988 (Box 9)
    - Landmark Theatre, 1987 (Box 9)
    - Mt. Vernon Library, 1991 (Box 9)
    - New Community Cinema, 1990 (Box 9)
    - New Jersey (Box 9)
    - New School, The (courses and lectures), 1989-1991 (Box 9)
    - New York, 1984 (Box 9)
    - Princeton University (Box 9)
    - Queens Museum of Art, 1996 (Box 9)
    - Rome, NY, 1990 (Box 9)
    - Rutgers University (Box 9)
    - Tacoma, 1992 (Box 9)
    - Toronto, 1990 (Box 9)
    - University of Connecticut, 1991 (Box 9)
    - University of Wisconsin, 1987 (Box 9)
    - Upstate Films, 1990 (Box 9)
    - Vassar College, 1993 (Box 9)
    - Westchester, 1991 (Box 9)
    - Wisconsin, 1984 (Box 9)
    - Missouri - Women's Jazz Festival, 1985 (Box 9)
    - Woodstock, 1985 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Presentations on Female Musicians, 1973-1994, (18 folders) (Box 10)
    Correspondence, programs, promotional material, reviews, and related materials from a variety of presentations and lectures by Reitz.
    - Bessie Smith Traditional Jazz Festival, 1991-1992 (Box 10)
    - Blues and Jazz Women, 1982 (Box 10)
    - Blues Lecture - Scarsdale High School, 1980-1981 (Box 10)
    - DeMaurier Downtown Jazz Festival - Toronto, Canada, 1990 (Box 10)
    - Guest Appearances on Various Radio Shows, 1973-1977 (Box 10)
    - History of African American Women in Music - Wellesley College (Box 10)
    - International Festival of Women's Film - Toronto, 1984 (Box 10)
    - Jazz Divas on Film - Lincoln Center, 1992 (Box 10)
    - Jazzwomen - Manhattan College (Box 10)
    - Mean Mothers (Box 10)
    - National Women's Hall of Fame - Bessie Smith Induction, 1984 (Box 10)
    - Ross Associates Women of Achievement, 1983 (Box 10)
    - Women are History, 1984 (Box 10)
    - Women in Blues - Smithsonian, 1985 (Box 10)
    - Women in Jazz, 1986-1994; (3 folders) (Box 10)
      Includes presentations at Utica College (1994), Woodstock (1993), and Greenwich House (1986).
    - Women's Jazz Festival - Kansas City, 1985 (Box 10)
- Writings Series, 1959-2006, (6 boxes)
  Throughout her career, Reitz wrote a number of fiction and non-fiction pieces, some of which were published and some of which remained in manuscript form. These included the book, Mushroom Cookery (1965) and a variety of articles on food that were primarily related to her work as a food critic in the 1960s; the book, Menopause: A Positive Approach (1977) and other writings on women's health and feminism primarily in the 1970s; and a number of ongoing projects related to music primarily in the 1980s and beyond. The majority of this series relates to Reitz's music writings, containing drafts, research notes, and related materials.
  - Women's Blues and Jazz: Their Magic 1920 to 1950s, manuscript, 1978-2006
    Book manuscript by Reitz that underwent several title changes during the course of its writing. Those included: The Blues Women: 1920-1950 (1978-1981), Mean Mothers and Their Sisters Shout the Independent Blues (1981-1987), Bessie to Billie: The Poetry of Women's Blues 1920 to 1950s (1997-1998), and Everywoman's Blues: Singers and Their Songs 1920 to 1950s (2000-2001).
    - Data CD titled Women's Blues and Jazz: Their Magic 1920 to 1950s, (1 Data CD, 89 PDF files) (Box 58)
      Complete drafts of each proposed chapter for the book manuscript Women's Blues and Jazz, along with related files, all in PDF format. Original titles retained.
    - Book Proposals, 1978-2006; (7 folders) (Box 11)
      Proposals to various presses of Women's Blues and Jazz and earlier versions. Arranged chronologically and by relative book title.
    - Chapter Drafts, (6 folders)
      - Dedication and Bibliography (Box 11)
      - Introductory Chapter (Box 11)
      - It's Tight Like That (Box 11)
      - The Precursors (Box 11)
      - Traditional Lines (Box 11)
      - Women's Reign (Box 11)
    - Manuscripts on Individual Musicians, (30 folders)
      Chapter-length writings, along with some associated research notes, that were either included or considered for inclusion in the book manuscript.
      - Alexander, Ora (Box 11)
      - Armstrong, Lil (Box 11)
      - Baker, LaVerne (Box 11)
      - Boswell, Connee (Box 11)
      - Brown, Ruth (Box 11)
      - Davis, Martha (Box 11)
      - Donegan, Dorothy (Box 11)
      - Dranes, Arizona (Box 11)
      - Edwards, Susie (Box 11)
      - Fields, Dorothy (Box 12)
      - Fitzgerald, Ella (Box 12)
      - Hall, Juanita (Box 12)
      - Holiday, Billie (Box 12)
      - Humes, Helen (Box 12)
      - Hunter, Alberta (Box 12)
      - Lee, Julia (Box 12)
      - McDaniel, Hattie (Box 12)
      - McRae, Carmen (Box 12)
      - McKinney, Nina Mae (Box 12)
      - Minnie, Memphis (Box 12)
      - Smith, Bessie (Box 12)
      - Smith, Trixie (Box 12)
      - Spivey, Victoria (Box 12)
      - Vaughan, Sarah (Box 12)
      - Wallace, Sippie, (2 folders) (Box 12)
      - Waters, Ethel (Box 12)
      - White, Georgia (Box 12)
      - Wiley, Lee (Box 12)
      - Wilson, Edith (Box 12)
    - Images, (14 folders) (Box 12)
      Non-photographic duplications of, and notes regarding, images considered for inclusion in the book manuscript. Arranged by relative chapter.
  - Other Unpublished Music Writings, 1977-1998 and undated
    Project ideas and unpublished manuscripts for a variety of music-related projects.
    - Blues is Like Chicken Soup (Box 13)
    - Classic Blues Queens (Box 13)
    - A Hot Romance: Lil and Louis (Box 13)
      Correspondence, chapter drafts, research notes, and related material for a book manuscript on the life and career of Lil Hardin Armstrong.
    - International Sweethearts of Rhythm Feature Film, 1992-1994; (4 folders) (Box 13)
      Correspondence, script drafts, research notes, and related material for a planned feature film written by Reitz, Bob Newman, and Beverly Sawyer along with an earlier script by Dianne Houston.
    - Project Ideas and Proposals, (21 folders)
      Correspondence, research notes, and related files for a variety of proposed artistic projects.
      - Book of the Month Club Record Proposal (Box 13)
      - Charlotte's Kidnapping (Box 13)
      - Composite Woman, 1992 (Box 13)
      - Heresies, 1980 (Box 13)
      - Hot Flashes Musical Revue, (2 folders) (Box 13)
        Contains song lyrics by Reitz along with research notes for the proposed revue.
      - The Lady Film (Box 14)
      - Legacy, 1991 (Box 14)
      - Madame C.J. Walker Film (Box 14)
      - Mean Mothers and Women's Blues at the Village Gate, 1980 (Box 14)
      - Mean Mothers Television Show, 1980 (Box 14)
      - Notes for a Novel, 1977-1980 (Box 14)
      - Shouters and Wailers Film, 1983-1985 (Box 14)
      - Sisters of Liberty Musical, 1986 (Box 14)
      - Valaida Film (Box 14)
      - Vogue Magazine Column Proposal, 1978 (Box 14)
      - Wild Women Don't Have the Blues - Savvy Magazine Proposal, 1980-1981 (Box 14)
      - A Woman's Jazz Band, 1992-1998 (Box 14)
      - Women in American Popular Song, 1981 (Box 14)
      - Women of Wall Street, 1988 (Box 14)
      - Women's Minstrelsy, 1998 (Box 14)
    - Related Research Notes, (3 folders) (Box 14)